<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>brasstistics</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://brasstistics.co.uk/</id><updated>2026-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>A day at the RNCM International Brass Band Festival</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/rncm-ibbf-2026.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2026-01-25:/rncm-ibbf-2026.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One and a half wonderful concerts at The RNCM International Brass Band Festival Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading to Manchester for The Royal Northern College of Music &lt;a href="https://www.rncm.ac.uk/festivals/rncm-international-brass-band-festival/"&gt;International Brass Band Festival&lt;/a&gt;, is another first for me. The event did not disappoint however and my only wish is I had caught more than the snippet I did. With exciting music both old and new being displayed by bands of the highest calibre the event was one that continued to push musical boundaries and raise these bands to the respected position they should hold in all musical circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three day event this year from the 23&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; to 25&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of February showcased 11 bands alongside 12 renowned soloists. Of this huge selection I was able to attend the set on Saturday by The Tredegar Town Band and Black Dyke Band. I have to admit that this was a choice mainly made by my own cherry picking of soprano classic "The Land of the Long White Cloud" by Philip Sparke along with the wish to show a visiting American friend new to brass bands la crème de la crème in Black Dyke. Many of the sets at this year's event were penned by Sparke with the festival as a whole celebrating his repertoire and marking his 75&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; birthday year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/RNCM_Trip_2026/Dyke.png" alt="Welcome" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;RNCM Concert Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering the RNCM building it became immediately clear this was an international event with multiple languages overheard even before entering the café doors. Once inside the main space it was also very clear how well subscribed the concert was to be along with how diverse in age the audience was. This was undoubtedly in part due to the excellent student and under 26 discount coupled with the many local students of the college in attendance. The large student attendance became extremely clear when players studying at The RNCM from both Tredegar and even more so Black Dyke received huge cheers from a large group section in the audience. It is to be commendable that the festival organisers are able to offer such rates to young people especially when there was an additional 20% reduction for attendance of three events or more. It is clear that these techniques work and I hope any other events will focus more on their target demographics in future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events were staged inside of the RNCM Concert Hall, which is the larger of the two spaces within the complex, seating ~700. It is no wonder therefore that the bar was crowded and that nearly every seat was occupied. Within the audience there was a clear academic skew with many well known banding faces in attendance from notable members from other bands not performing at the event to conductors, composers. What was refreshing was that this group was also supplemented with members of the public when bands with household names were playing. Speaking to one woman next to me, who did not play an instrument nor recognise the name Tredegar said she attended every year to see Black Dyke. This speaks volumes about the music selected that it can both cater to clientele who require world premieres, boundary pushing commissions and virtuosic solos as well as attracting those who wish to only attend a single concert by their favourite band. As someone closer to the single concert group I awaited Tredegar's set with anticipation for some interesting though perhaps abstract works. And while they did deliver a performance with plenty academic rigour the content and accompanying descriptions before each piece allowed for an informed enjoyment of their works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conductor:&lt;/strong&gt; Ian Porthouse&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tamsin Crook&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;A Spark Forgotten&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Derek Bourgeois&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Euphonium Concerto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Soloist:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Glenn Van Looy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phil Lawrence&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Melisande&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(World Premiere)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philip Sparke&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Land of the Long White Cloud&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the set was a very recent commission "&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nV3vlYnj8p0"&gt;A Spark Forgotten&lt;/a&gt;" (2025) composed by &lt;b&gt;Tamsin Crook&lt;/b&gt; a cornet and arranger from Cumbria. The piece bursts with a building mysterious energy and has great moments for percussion which shine in a very barren band supporting them. And what a percussion collection it was a group of seven in all black sit at the back though for this piece only four are involved. This gave me a slight Chekhov's percussionist feeling though the payoff would have to wait for another two pieces time. The band built to a driving finish and huge applause which was also offered to Tamsin who was in attendance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/RNCM_Trip_2026/Tredegar.png" alt="Tredegar1" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;RNCM Concert Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceeding onwards a stunning performance of the "&lt;a href="https://www.worldofbrass.com/100619-download"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Derek Bourgeois&lt;/b&gt; Euphonium Concerto&lt;/a&gt;" (1990) was given by guest soloist &lt;a href="https://genevainstruments.com/geneva-artist/glenn-van-looy/?srsltid=AfmBOorb4lhnLx7apXrAykt11wqghfqFAVaFpofynzc22NdM5bo07tNw"&gt;Glenn Van Looy&lt;/a&gt;. This concerto is one that both parties know well having previously collaborated on it for Glenn's 2019 release "Step Out" on the Chandos label. Knowing they had climbed this mountain before I think played a key role in the relaxed and confident performance produced by both the band and soloist. With huge extremes taken in both frequency and dynamic range Glenn took time to savour the apexes of lyrical passages and hold tight to near perfect intonation across at least four octaves. The accompanying band also pushed their own limits with whisper like muted sections from their five basses and cheeky smiles shared between soloist Glenn and soprano cornet Rob Westacott as they chased ever higher in call and response. Though in the second movement devilishly high, fast, solo sections did lead some players to trip and set off others like dominoes, the overall performance was one which rightfully impressed all present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was most pleasantly surprised by &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6Qd2MidyXTQ"&gt;Melisande&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;b&gt;Phil Lawrence&lt;/b&gt; which proved to my favourite piece of the day. The topic of the piece focuses on the composer's own dog, Mélisande, and her short life. In a description of the work Lawrence writes that the piece is a "heartfelt tribute to her life, celebrating her as an irreplaceable and cherished member of our family". The work follows her from birth, playful years as a puppy and the role she played as a dedicated mother. While describing the section in which Mélisande chases a butterfly, Ian Porthouse took a moment to point out the butterfly, portrayed by principal cornet, Dewi Griffiths, who did indeed later flit and float very well. The work was also chosen in memory of Phil Lawrence who sadly passed after a short battle with cancer in June 2025 and whose family were in attendance at this world premiere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece itself was a delight. The required seven Chekhov's percussionists were awakened and were instantly sent into action as the piece and birth of Mélisande began in "The spark of birth". Starting with the first of many wonderfully weird percussion instructions a lonely octave is played on "Vibraphone upper 8va bowed, lower 8vb with stick" which hangs waiting for life to begin in the form of the cornets giving the first indication of the cheeky dog about to join us. The repeated percussion followed by cheeky moving cornet lines accelerates and gives the feeling of an engine crank slowly catching more and more building up a heartbeat which becomes the ever changing excited beginning of her puppy years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/RNCM_Trip_2026/Meli.png" alt="Mélisande" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Mélisande photo taken from Obrasso.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The percussion within the puppy years is a wonder to watch with them not given a second's rest as new sounds appear and disappear and Mélisande discovers the world. The score turns into an essay of descriptors such as "football rattlecrank fast", "whip", "tambourine on snare drum skin" and "metal beater scrape from centre of suspended cymbal out to edge very quickly" which nail the depiction of a life filled with novelty at each step. So too in the cornet section Lawrence includes instructions for changes of mutes along with markings for "fltz", "HOB" and "upper note player does Wah" so the cornets aren't left to dawdle. Eventually the percussive chaos settles into everyday life and the personality of the Irish Red Setter shines through as she goes on adventures with a friendly tortoise, fish and a squirrel. Eventually Mélisande becomes a mother and gorgeous bell tree motifs are added replicating, in my mind, the sound of the descending diatonic major scales of church bells. This is followed by a rousing conclusion which had a feel of a triumphant film score. The performance itself was a joy with a playful, light quality that acted as a palate cleanser in the set as well as showcasing the great percussion team in this expanded band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish I was treated to "Land of the Long White Cloud" by &lt;b&gt;Philip Sparke&lt;/b&gt;. Though I knew this had the gorgeous soprano cornet line I had purposefully kept myself from hearing it before the event in the hope of enjoying each section live for the first time. The shock of the triumphant full band opening was therefore a complete but welcome surprise. The hymn-like quality of the melody carried by horns down to lower brass was carried wonderfully by Tredegar and the tune reminded me strangely of a hymn from my childhood &lt;a href="https://music.churchofscotland.org.uk/hymn/191-do-not-be-afraid-for-i-have-redeemed-you"&gt;Do not be afraid, for I have redeemed you&lt;/a&gt; though I am certain there is no connection given the depiction of New Zealand this piece produces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally penned as the set work for the New Zealand Brass Band Association National Championships (1979) and was Sparke's first arrangement for competition. It is therefore no wonder that every member of the band is worked so hard, none more so than Rob Westacott on soprano who rose to the occasion. With extraordinary stabs from on high, he punctuated against the rest of the band into the short driving march-like section. Truly the man of the match even before reaching the soprano solo making massive impact on the shape of the work. Passing quickly through 2/4 to 6/8 melody in the lower brass that reminds me a bustling city with muted cornet car horns we reach a sudden silence that marks the sparse apex and the entrance of a haunting soprano melody which was handled with ease. This powerful return to the soprano motif in lower brass with accompanying fanfare is rousing before one final drop to an excellent pianissimo standstill and an accelerating dash back through the previous themes towards an immense finish and deserved applause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a break for dinner at &lt;a href="https://bundobust.com/"&gt;Bundobust&lt;/a&gt;, (All veggie Indian tapas well worth a go!), I returned to enjoy a second set by The Black Dyke Band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conductor:&lt;/strong&gt; Professor Nicholas Childs&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paul Lovatt-Cooper&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Fanfare for Bradford&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bruce Broughton&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Wildfire&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(World Premiere)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philip Sparke&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Gemini&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Soloists:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Tom Hutchinson&lt;/em&gt; – cornet, &lt;em&gt;Adam Bokaris&lt;/em&gt; – euphonium&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;(World Premiere for Brass Band)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edward Gregson&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Symphony in Two Movements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;~Interval~&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simon Dobson&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Percussion Concerto&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Soloist:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Yasuaki Fukuhara&lt;/em&gt; – percussion&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;(World Premiere)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Ottorino Respighi, arr. &lt;strong&gt;Howard Snell&lt;/strong&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Feste Romane&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least most of a set... Sadly given my need to not sleep on the streets and Northern Rail's lack of services I was only able to enjoy the first half before treating myself to a rail replacement bus back to Lancaster. Still any opportunity to enjoy Black Dyke is a great treat and this occasion proved no different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular concert was billed to be the high point of the festival with the occasion being recorded for use on BBC Radio 3 and can be listened to &lt;a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m002r48c"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This excellent opportunity for raising the profile of banding to the wider classical audiences was not missed by the players of Black Dyke as well as the audience. This lead to both an excellent performance and some of the loudest cheers heard in the day as everyone from the community wished success upon the venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/RNCM_Trip_2026/Dyke_BBC.png" alt="Dyke1" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Black Dyke being introduced for BBC Radio 3.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceedings were opened with "Fanfare for Bradford" written by &lt;b&gt;Paul Lovatt-Cooper&lt;/b&gt; which lifted the energy even higher following the huge cheers for Professor Nicholas Childs. Following the short fanfare an interesting interview was conducted with &lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://brucebroughton.com/broughtons-wildfire-for-brass-to-premiere-in-manchester/"&gt;Bruce Broughton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; composer of Wildfire. While all the content within the interview was excellent, because of the length of time it continued for the energy within the hall began to wane. Indeed even some of the players on stage began to let their smiles fade as they waited to be unleashed upon Wildfire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interview focused on the structure of the piece and how it depicts the terrifying 2025 Los Angeles fires. This is a topic I was aware of through the news and the videos shared by renowned trumpeter, Jens Lindemann, who himself &lt;a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/RebuildMusicJens"&gt;fundraised&lt;/a&gt; after losing his home in the Pacific Palisades fires. At the time of these events, Broughton himself began writing but eventually was forced to leave his home as the flames approached, unsure if he would return. This power of the fire was the inspiration for the first section of the piece and it was reflected clearly in the work with the band working hard throughout on endless runs depicting the expansion. Broughton also discussed that he did not want a triumphant finish to the piece due to the horrid nature of the event but instead turning to the bravery of the firefighters for inspiration to close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Gemini" proved an entertaining and charismatic piece with both soloists &lt;em&gt;Tom Hutchinson&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Adam Bokaris&lt;/em&gt; giving a relaxed performance despite the extreme requirements of the work. Some passages from Bokaris were difficult to hear clearly which I initially put down to his further distance. Perhaps it is however more likely to be a consequence of the change in tonal colour when the piece was restructured for brass band from the original wind arrangement. In the quieter sections and breaks the techniques of both soloists shine through clearly highlighting the abilities and tonal colour of both instruments. This new premiere of the work rewritten also acted as a test of Hutchinson after his recent move to Black Dyke. He clearly rose to the occasion with the incredibly fast joint lines which slotted perfectly in tone alongside the already settled Bokaris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish my abridged version of the concert, I was treated to &lt;b&gt;Edward Gregson's&lt;/b&gt; "Symphony in Two Movements" (2012) which has had a huge outing in 2025 as the set work for the National Brass Band Championships of Great Britain. I was lucky enough to attend this year's national final in The Royal Albert Hall and therefore was excited to see if the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; place recital would be repeated as previously in London. Comparing my notes between the two performances I felt that the tempos had been adjusted relative to the original listening. This was especially clear in the much faster opening and later at bar 357 when the ringing tam tam marked "LUNGA" seemed decidedly corta. I am not here to give any advice or instruction however and only want to say that I missed the hanging silence following the tam tam. Though perhaps this is just a less contest-centered performance without the need to overaccentuate for adjudicators. The ending was just as excellent as the first time I heard it performed with the mixture of tubular bells ringing out and trombones giving a rousing hunting horn fanfare to herald the conclusion. After hearing the iconic tutti band accented tenuto crotchets both the set and my day trip to Manchester were at an end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day trip and review would not be complete however without one last look at another brassy icon from the north... Divina De Campo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; justify-content: center; gap: 10px;"&gt;
    &lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/RNCM_Trip_2026/Campo.png" alt="Brig" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Outfit worn in the "queen of your hometown" challenge, episode 1, series 1 of RuPaul's Drag Race UK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With outfits nearly as iconic as the purple uniforms, it's not hard to guess why she is billed as the second best thing to come out of Brighouse. I stumbled across this one used in RuPaul's Drag Race season 1 while in Afflecks in the Northern Quarter. I highly recommend giving it a watch especially since drag and brass band contesting are two of the only competitive artforms in the world! Perhaps there is more to be learned than has already been gained at events such as &lt;a href="https://www.4barsrest.com/news/60521/kinky-toots-success-in-Blackpool"&gt;Kinky Toots&lt;/a&gt;... New uniform anyone?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="concerts"/><category term="travel"/><category term="RNCM"/></entry><entry><title>Update - RNCM International Brass Band Festival</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/rncm-update.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2026-01-23:/rncm-update.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Off to see the Wizard (David Thornton) at the RNCM International Brass Band Festival. International means Manchester these days...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I dare to leave Lancaster and head to the big smoke, Manchester, for The Royal Northern College of Music &lt;a href="https://www.rncm.ac.uk/festivals/rncm-international-brass-band-festival/"&gt;International Brass Band Festival&lt;/a&gt; Spearheaded by David Thornton. This year the event celebrates &lt;a href="https://www.philipsparke.com/biography"&gt;Philip Sparke&lt;/a&gt; in this his 75th year. I will attend the performance of Tredegar Town Band who will also accompany euphonium star Glenn Van Looy. I also intend to see the first half of Black Dyke Band's performance though due to a lack of Northern Rail trains late at night, the first half will be as much as I can see. Still seeing three world premiers is a lot all the same!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Updates/RNCM_Update.png" alt="pride 1" style="height:200px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Updates"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="concerts"/><category term="travel"/></entry><entry><title>East to West</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/east-to-west.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2026-01-10:/east-to-west.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brass in Concert to The Areas - My contest re-education&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite many trips to UniBrass and Whit Friday, 2024-25 was the first year I began to attend the key contests that form the backbone of the banding calendar. It all started when my band Lancaster University won the shield award at UniBrass 2024 in Warwick. In turn, this led to us being invited up to be the Brass in Concert reception band in November 2024. I'm ashamed to say it now given how impactful the event is but it was my first time hearing of BIC (other than the pen...) but I will allow myself some slack given I am a first generation bander trained in a north west non-contesting band. I have to say however that looking back it was well worth the slow cross rail train up to the toon and that it has started a chain reaction which is still in full effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Bridge1.png" alt="BIC 0" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt; Tyne Bridge and the Glasshouse (Sage) the night before BIC.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Bridge2.png" alt="BIC 1" style="height:220px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Night mode.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Bus.png" alt="BIC 2" style="height:220px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Trip sponsored by Go North East.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After arriving to the Glasshouse (previously The Sage) our band played a set covering our Pendle Witch Trail theme which we had taken to Warwick. This time with new members and the cheeky addition of my brother on Euphonium despite him not ever being a Lancaster student or ever competing in UniBrass. Sorry contest control...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/ULMSBB1.png" alt="BIC 3" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;ULMS Brass Band in the atrium.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/ULMSBB2.png" alt="BIC 4" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;ULMS Brass Band performing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the performance &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ZLnJm22zaR0?si=V_eup2UmKcRareky"&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the day was spent in the hall very close to the contest action. Had it not been down to my bad planning I would have even had my predictions to compare to the results but alas for lack of a pen the data was lost... A good time was had all the same although it did become a loud day given we were booked in row B opposite the soprano players. Though this was definitely more than fine with me given I have been playing soprano myself that morning. Proof of our being there was even captured with my brother being caught in a cooperation band selfie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/On_Stage.png" alt="BIC 5" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Plenty of brass fish in the sea. But they didn't cast the net very far.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Stage.png" alt="BIC 6" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;The fish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did he know that within a year’s time he would be on the very same stage with that very band!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Glasshouse proved an incredible venue and I was very much inspired by the variety of sets. My highlight was Paul Richard's controlled performance of "Beyond the Veil" by Thibaut Bruniaux which was carefully accompanied by the creative percussion section on a host of interesting items from slinkies to "sound tubes", which piqued my interest as a physicist. Though I was also completely drawn in by Richard Poole's performance of "Blowin' In The Wind" arranged by John Barber. Cory also gave a stellar winning set complete with, the now very topical,  turned backs to the audience while they performed the gorgeous "Around the Campfire" by Philip Harper in their set around the "The Magnificent Seven".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Newcastle I headed to the brass big apple, Blackpool, for The North West Areas. Starting early I managed to thumb a lift to the rainy seaside with some of the university players who are members of Pilling Band. After the draw and listening to their rehearsal in a strange part theatre part antiques Aladdin's cave we headed to the Winter Gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking into the main hall under the domed glass ceiling was a real treat though slightly dizzying given you have to dodge the known brass world having a yearly catch up. Even stranger still is to find a moment of peace inside a Spanish Galleon. Luckily finding the bar did mean I was heading the right direction to watch the 3rd section bands clash inside of the Spanish Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entering I was greeted by Band 2 (Trinity Girls) and the opening of Arkansas by Jacob de Haan. This was my first chance to hear a set test piece contest so I settled myself and made amends for my forgotten notepad in Newcastle by writing far too much. The hall while acoustically strange (being flat and long), is very inspiring with ornate scenes of coastal towers and villas. Despite these I kept my jacket on throughout and found myself rewarded when rain began falling on me through the glass ceiling. Despite the slightly wet notepad I still had a great time given the light and narrative set work and I soon found myself at band 10 going for a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Spanish_Hall.png" alt="Areas 1" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;The Spanish Hall in the Winter Gardens Theatre.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post lunch I realised the draw blessed me with an excellent double act of Fodens directly followed by Leyland performing Diversions by Derek Bourgeois so I made my way to the Opera House. With both bands getting later draws (8th 9th) and knowing Fodens' track record of winning the then last 8 (now 9 2014-20, 2022-25) North West Areas I expected a great performance and they definitely delivered. The impactful opening directly into bustling main theme variations made such a change compared to Arkansas especially given the abstract/lack of specified subject matter. I was spoilt to hear the piece for the first time played by the winning band, but even despite my lack of comparison I could tell their controlled drop in dynamics into multiple exposed soloists meant they were on for great things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The apex of Fodens' rendition however came in the form of their expert blending of a single lyrical line in the second movement moving seamlessly from flugel to principal cornet followed by Soprano. The hand off between Mark Wilkinson and Richard Poole was so indistinguishable in tone and was no doubt the product of their long tenure playing together in the same band since 2002. This long lasting understanding in their playing was further highlighted when compared to the same passing of the tune completed by the excellent Andrew Lofthouse and Lewis Barton who are both superb but have only had a year of playing under the same baton. Both renditions were excellent with the judges later commenting that of all the bands only two or three truly hit the mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Hall.png" alt="Areas 2" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;A good band must have been playing for the atrium to be this empty. Maybe the bar just opened...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/Area_Stage.png" alt="Areas 3" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Championship section stage (The Opera House).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of judges lets see how I did compared to the only ears that mattered those of Nicholas Garman and Paul Norley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/BIC_Stats_1.png" alt="Areas 4" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Real judge placing vs my prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly I was never going to be on the money after missing 6 bands... But at least you can see that we're singing from the same hymn sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plotting my ranking against the judges own and the case where you agree with the judges (y=x) allows for some comparison. Both the judges predictions and mine have a similar symmetry along the agreement line suggesting that although individual bands are placed differently there is similarity to the overall shape of our placings even if we disagree for specific bands. My rankings are however far below the agreement line due to the fact I only ranked the bands I watched giving them positions 1 to 8 missing. This fails to reflect there could be other bands placed between them. To try and show this more clearly you can imagine I could space the bands I did see evenly between 1 and 14. This is equivalent to scaling my own scores by the number of bands I saw multiplied by the total number of competitors eg* 14/8. This does lead to some tricky "positions" such as 1.75th place being my winner but let's do the maths first and ask questions later...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/BIC_Stats_2.png" alt="Areas 5" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Rescaled placings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/Brass_Adventures/BIC_Stats_3.png" alt="Areas 6" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Residual between the judges and my prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly overall the numbers are more reasonably distributed around the agreement line now, though there are still plenty of bands that I have placed far from the judges ranking too. Still not too bad for a first attempt, but just like with playing music I'll stick to the day job...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events were inspiring however I am thankful that I was able to attend them in the order I did. Despite the glitz, polished sets and full audiences of BIC the drizzly day in Blackpool also offered plenty of allure even if the surroundings felt like a time capsule. The Winter Gardens lack of amenities is however not the main culprit when it comes to the numbers who attend. This is however only the case as the current audience is from a very small pot of brass banders themselves who want to listen to bands at an event ran by banders. This is in sharp contrast to the very commercial enterprise that is BIC which focuses more heavily on who they attract to the event and what their event offers. Despite some dilapidation in places, the chance to experience the Areas and their deep historical connections with their venues makes the trip worthwhile. This is also something that cannot be easily recreated in shiny new locations and venues especially when they change their name so often... The North West Areas experience is therefore something that should be enjoyed while it is still alive and kicking. Especially given the current rational focus within banding on survival which was highlighted this year passed by the decision to move the spring festival to Birmingham and out of Blackpool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these events serve different purposes and have unique battles to fight to ensure their futures, both share an excellent energy spanning from their dedicated volunteers and the bands they serve year round. I thoroughly recommend attendance at both and personally cannot wait to return year on year. No matter which coast you go to you cannot go wrong with a trip to the seaside to hear some great music.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="stats"/><category term="Brass in Concert"/><category term="BIC"/><category term="Areas"/></entry><entry><title>A Pint Whit Cheese and Crackers</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/whit-friday-2025.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2026-01-01:/whit-friday-2025.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another year another silly costume at Whit Friday! All fine until you start bumping into celebrities...&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest free show on earth- or banders Christmas arrived quickly this year, and I’m ashamed to admit that I was unprepared. Normally I have my costume ready well in advance thanks to Lancaster University Brass Band's (ULMS BB) habit of dressing up year-round for bar crawls. Though this year the pesky studying made it hard to start putting one together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year for the theme it was a toss up between Taylor Swift or our friends from down the road in Preston, Wallace and Gromit. Though these themes seem a misstep to me when we could have dressed in parkas to celebrate Oasis's return. Though maybe that is just my love for &lt;a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/4sBxnCk1CSuMXCHAMIQlTh?si=WUMw7G0ESBuisTollHz1NQ"&gt;Cory Brit-Pop&lt;/a&gt; talking. In the end the brass reps saw sense and this year we dressed as the clay wonders. Which for me meant finding stuff to dress as the rabbit Hutch (not the cornet player)..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/Hutch1.png" alt="Hutch1" style="height:180px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Hutch.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/hutchish.png" alt="Hutch2" style="height:180px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Hutch-ish.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/Hutch-est.png" alt="Hutch3" style="height:180px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Hutch-est-Hutch?.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One treat I got the band this year was a logo for our bass drum. Only a few air bubbles got in while we put it on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/drum.png" alt="BIC 0" style="height:250px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year luckily our coach arrived crash free (long may it continue) to campus and we headed off in the direction of Saddleworth. The circuit this year (and every year) started at Lydgate. Since everyone in the band bar deps are lazy students and prefer to ditch studying early we once again were the first band to arrive leaving time for photos and a drink. Surprisingly the pubs reaction to our costumes was very tame. I can only assume they were disappointed after last year we invaded The White Hart with 15 versions of The Mystery Gang for our &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/B4lvu8N0WOw?si=_WcGb2GYpLJBviMP"&gt;Scooby-Doo&lt;/a&gt; theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
     &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/band0.png" alt="BIC 0" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Lydgate we moved to Greenfield after a small wrong turn by our bus driver. Even with us going early, we were  not destined to be second or third to play however due to the cue of bands reaching back to Tescos. Despite how early in the day it was there were plenty bands and even more listeners at both the road march and field. The wait was a positive in the end as it allowed me to have a chat with Max Standard who is an alumnus of the band, conductor and composer of one of our UniBrass set pieces &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/O5TgPf3UXhs?si=xTXj-Lpl1-5Dq8So"&gt;"Into the Future"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Greenfield to Friezland where our second brass rep and local legend Alex appeared after sitting an exam. Not wishing to lag behind after missing two villages, Alex had brought along with him a box of 60 confetti cannons. This was a complete revelation to the band but we soon got the idea when a cannon exploded at the end of every four bars in the Wallace and Gromit road march. I can only think the cannons must have deafened the adjudicators, because they awarded us the 'Best University Prize' for the first time ever! £100! And I even got a nice mention in the crit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/band2.png" alt="Uppermill" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Brace for impact.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came Uppermill and after pushing our way through the incredible crowd and having some chips we took the road up to my personal favorite Dobcross. I was lucky this year to have my parents come along, and they both gave the soprano cornet their best while we listened to the incredible Fairey Band perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/bus.png" alt="Dobcross1" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;I maintain that holding the instrument is 50% of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/top_notes.png" alt="Dobcross2" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Triple C.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After playing our standing march we were all very surprised when someone with a familiar voice came over to talk to our guest conductor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/DobX.png" alt="Dobcross2.5" style="height:300px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Thanks Cathy!&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it was Ben Whitehead, voice of Wallace! What are the chances?! Ben was lovely to the band and indulged us with lots of photos with the obligatory "Cheese Gromit" before the flash. What was even more surprising was that he loved brass bands too even knowing our march "Star Lake" and appreciating that it was lesser played! Meet your heroes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/Band_Ben.png" alt="Dobcross3" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Ben with the band... Also my parents... Also some locals...&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/Ben.png" alt="Dobcross4" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Not much of a resemblance to Wallace.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the sun began to set we arrived at the obvious best village to finish at, Delph. With registration closing and the cue of bands huge, we had plenty time to enjoy a few road marches before it was our turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/DELPH.png" alt="Delph1" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;View before the chaos. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/Delph_walk.png" alt="Delph2" style="height:270px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walk down was a treat and ended with the remainder (more than half) of the box of confetti cannons being set off. It was a wonderful big finish and a happy last outing for me at university on my sop. Though for some of our members, the return to university drinking and marching proved too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/A_Pint_Whit_Cheese_and_Crackers/long_day.png" alt="Delph3" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;ZzzzZZZzzzZzzzZZz&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the day unfold in &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/OM-0D3KgeeI?si=d3yUSezdS7cON5JW"&gt;"A Grand Whit Fri-day Out"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="stats"/><category term="Whit Friday"/><category term="Whit Friday 2025"/><category term="university"/></entry><entry><title>Brass-ed From the Past</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/brass-ed-from-the-past.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2025-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2025-11-03:/brass-ed-from-the-past.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anything but maths.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While digging into data is the reason we are here on this earth, I also hope to use this page to show the musical trips I take when playing or listening. It’s been a great summer for brass and I have plenty to talk about so we'll start there and go ever onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="display: flex; gap: 10px; justify-content: center;"&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/co_park.jpg" alt="pride 1" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Marching with the co.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/co_sub.jpg" alt="pride 2" style="height:280px;"&gt;
        &lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;Subway with the co.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Updates"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="contests"/><category term="concerts"/><category term="travel"/></entry><entry><title>Brasstistics Launch</title><link href="https://brasstistics.co.uk/launch.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2025-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Scott Henderson</name></author><id>tag:brasstistics.co.uk,2025-11-02:/launch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brass meets stats&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- PELICAN\_END\_SUMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to **Brasstistics** — a home for analysis and visualization of brass band results!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Articles"/><category term="launch"/><category term="brass band"/><category term="stats"/></entry></feed>